安。
本會現在恢復《合約第三者權利條例草案》二讀辯論，審議條例草案嘅委員會主席梁繼昌議員就委員會嘅報告向本會發言，梁議員。
先生，主席，在我擔任《議事委員會》關於《合約權益第三方法案》主席委員會主席的職務下，我報告《議事委員會》的討論。
法案委員會支持《的合同權或第三方法案》，簡稱《法案》。
which seeks to provide for the enforcement of contractual terms by third parties and related matters.
委員會指出，這係應對香港律師公會提出之擔憂。
deeds of mutual covenants, DMCs。
are to be excluded from the application of the bill.
因為律法relevant to building management and enforcement of rights under a DMC。
consist of a range of applicable legal provisions under the Building Management Ordinance, Chapter 344.
《The Conveyancing and Property Ordinance》第219章和《The Common Law》。
這些適用的法律原則，創造一個獨特且複雜的法律體係，which sets clear limits on the enforceability of land covenants.
The current legal regime for the enforcement of a DMC has, over the years, developed specifically in response to the needs of regulating the occupation and management of multi-storey buildings and estate developments in Hong Kong.
任何 change to the DMC regime will affect a large number of people, and it would be inappropriate for the bill to alter or relax the legal regime of DMC.
Without full consultation, specifically aimed at reform of this branch of the law.
to address the issue that a DMC may contain terms not relating to land.
The administration has proposed to amend clause three, sub-section two of the bill.
所以，為咗釐清，所有條文喺一個DMC。
作為一個契約，relating to land.
are to be excluded from the application of the bill.
法案委員會已就是否排除DMCs從法案適用範圍內，會使私人建築物的租客，
和使用者，Common Parts of Private Buildings。
Who are not owners of the private buildings, unable to rely on the bill, to enforce a term of the DMC.
According to the Department of Justice.
作為租客，私有建築物。
and users of common parts of private buildings, are not owners of
私人建築。
They are generally not entitled to bring an action under a DMC.
The exclusion of a DMC from the application of the bill does not act or diminish the rights under the DMC.
Neither does the exclusion preclude contracting parties.
If they so intend.
from from conferring an enforceable right of action.
Against a tenant.
或一使用者， of the common parts of a private building.
所以，長，作為，要求。
Under other applicable laws, are complied with.
委員會主席：，委員會主席，先生，指出，一個第三方。
可以 presently seek to enforce a contract from the court through devices such as agency and trust.
Members of the Bills Committee have asked whether the rights of the third party to enforce a contract would be diminished following the implementation of the bill.
As clarified by the Department of Justice, the bill, if implemented, would provide a third party with an additional channel, which is more convenient, to enforce the contract.
如果它是承諾方的意圖，允許第三方執行合約。
Mr. President.
The objective of the present reform is to confer rights on a third party.
rather than to derogate from them.
thus, the existing rights of a third party under statute law and at common law would not be affected after the implementation of the bill.
on the implementation arrangements.
The administration has been asked to step up publicity efforts in the promotion of the new legislative regime.
with a view to assisting the general public and various stakeholders in preparing for the implementation of the bill.
In response to members' suggestions.
The administration has advised that it would liaise closely with the legal professional bodies in this regard.
The administration also agreed to consider the feasibility of bringing the new legislative regime into operation one year after the passage of the bill.
Next, Mr. President, I would like to give my personal views on this bill.
Mr. President, the doctrine of privy of contract provides that a person who is not a party to a contract cannot acquire any rights under that contract.
或被subject to any of his burden。
this remains the general rules in Hong Kong law.
The fact that a third-party beneficiary of a contract.
Could not enforce the contractual benefits in his favour, was generally regarded as unsatisfactory.
and indeed, a number of devices were developed in the past in order to circumvent this aspect of privy doctrine.
In addition, a number of exceptions.
were developed where third-party rights were recognised.
這些devices and exceptions，可以 artificial and complex。
所以，那有理由為改革第三方受益人制度。
這些 devise,s and exceptions remain, despite the enactment of the bill.
The bill follows the major contents and direction of the English contracts.
In bracket, Rights of Third Party Act, 1999.
very generally speaking.
The bill allows a third party to a contract the right of enforcement, provided that either limb of a two-limbs test is satisfied.
First, either that a third party may enforce the contract.
If the contract contains an express term to that effect.
或。
If the contract contains a term which purports to confer a benefit on a third party,
那 party may enforce that term， unless on a proper construction of the contract.
The parties to the contract do not intend the third party may do so.
先生，我支持通過該法案。
Indeed, I think the bill should come at an earlier date, so that Hong Kong's contract law system can be more in line with that of most other common law jurisdictions.
There are three types of contracts which I would like to mention here.
這些係合同，which would have more bearings on the daily lives of the citizens of Hong Kong.
第一，合同規管的關係之間，僱主和僱員。
先生，條法案唔會alter啲合約協議，訂立喺之間嘅僱主同僱員。
在的，能力，或，對，一，份，就業，契約。
然而，the bill contains a provision under clause three, subsection four.
要 prohibit a third party from enforcing a term of employment against an employee by a third party.
This provision does not apply to an employer.
In simple terms, a third party may still be able to enforce a term of an employment contract against an employer.
Provided conditions of the enforceability requirement in the bill are satisfied.
這條款給更多保護給一個員工。
Who is often seen as the party with the weaker bargaining power in an employment relationship?
第二，我亦都Concerned about consumer rights in a consumer contract.
The honourable Dennis Quaid raised a question in the 7 May 2014 Bills Committee meeting.
essentially， the requirement of the enforceability test under Clause 4 of the bill.
which I have highlighted about, above will not enable consumers to have direct and convenient remedies for damages.
injury or loss suffered due to a breach of a contract.
to which he was not a party to.
呢個觀點確實係由消費者諮詢委員會所分享。
政府在應對此關切時，明確表示，政府與法律改革委員會共識。
and considered that it is more appropriate to give effect.
to the contracting parties' intention.
whether to confer legally enforceable right on a third party.
This response, I believe, is not satisfactory.
And I would urge the government to review this aspect of the bill at an appropriate time.
now，indeed，would，the，government，let，me，know。
The redress and remedies a consumer can obtain if he is injured by a faulty product as a consumer, but nonetheless he is not a party to a consumer contract.
我認為任何聲稱都可以進行。
Under a tortious claim hat.
或，個 statutory claim under any product liability legislation.
但我會非常 grateful if the government can confirm that point.
Third, it is important to note that insurance contract is not excluded from the bill, so it would be possible for parties to an insurance contract.
to exclude the operation of the bill in the contract.
Through proper construction of the policy wording, if the party so intended.
在contest of insurance contracts.
我因此關心，這項保險的對象。
Who may not be a party to insurance contract? Maybe he is not paying the premium.
may not be able to enforce such a contract.
在terms of the complexity and technical nature of the bill.
and the fact that normal citizens and consumers in general will be affected by the bill.
我會勸促政府，和 indeed律師公會，要投入足夠的資源和時間，去教育公眾，關於法案的影響力，於法案通過之前。
And I would like the government to give an undertaking in this council to do so.
last, on behalf of my constituents.
我會要求政府明確地釐清法案對企業文件的影響。
The first type of document I'm concerned about is the constitutive documents of a Hong Kong incorporated company.
I.E. the memorandum of association under the new companies ordinance.
現在，什麼是該法案對傳統上只綁束股東和公司的憲法文件的影響？
and secondly.
what is the effect of the bill on any public offer documents for shares or securities offered to the public?
under the companies ordinance.
所有的 Securities and Futures Ordinance。
the proper construction of the second question, I believe, of any public who subscribes for shares or securities.
Under public order document.
should be a party to a contract.
而The terms of the public offer document would become the terms of the subscription.
Therefore，those subscribers are not third party to such a subscription contract.
任何 purported exclusion clause drafted under the bill will have no effect on the subscribers.
Please, will the government confirm that my understanding is correct here?
主席。
subject to my above comments, I support, and would urge my honouring members of the council from across the political parties to support the resumption of the second reading and the passage of the bill. Thank you, Mr. President.有冇其他議員想發言？
李慧瓊業。
主席，本條例草案係喺香港合約法嘅框架底下引入讓第三者強制執行授予佢嘅權利，呢個做法係打破咗過去唔係合約一方就唔能夠根據合約而取得強制執行權。
按照過往嘅原則，合約各方就算想令第三者受惠，除非第三者係藉助代理或者信託等法律原則。
去協助執行，誒，否則咧，若然係無法執行咧，喺現行嘅合約法框架底下咧，亦都不能夠落實。
所以咧，經常畀人批評咧，係會作出一啲令人牽強嘅決定，而且亦都違背咗合約各方咧要令第三者受惠嘅意願。喺某種情況底下咧，第三者為咗強制執行有關嘅權利咧，就需要用。
大量分開訂立嘅合約，等等呢啲形式咧，去執行招致額外嘅費用，造成複雜同埋不便。主席面對呢個不理想嘅情況咧，好多嘅普通法嘅司法管轄區已經通過立法改革呢個原則。呢啲司法管轄區咧，包括澳大利亞、加拿大、英。
英國、新西蘭同埋新加坡，主席民建聯咧係支持法改會多年前發表嘅《納約各方嘅相互關係報告書》，建議透過詳細嘅立法機制改革目前《納約各方相互關係原則》，亦都支持通過本條例草案去落實法改會嘅建議，以改善香港合。
約法制度，以使制度能夠與其他主要普通法司法管轄區做法看齊。
主席，追本溯源，立法各方嘅相互關係報告書早喺二零零五年九月已經發表，但係由建議到立法到生效，前後差不多經歷咧十年。呢個咧再次説明香港喺唔同嘅範疇嘅發展咧，都係以龜速前進。呢個情況咧，絕對係一個警號。
為咗提升香港嘅競爭能力，去喺唔同層面上競爭能力咧，特區政府咧必須檢視每個環節，點對點諗諗咧點樣可以加快完善咧法規嘅程序。主席用讓第三者強制執行授予佢嘅權力，第一步。
呢一步咧，香港雖然走得好慢、好細，英國咧喺一九九九年咧已經引入合約第三者權利法例，但係無論如何，作為第一步咧，今次嘅修訂係參考咗英國同埋其他國家落實相關法例後嘅案例，平衡咗合約方嘅意願同埋第三者嘅權益，亦都合，亦都。
考慮咗香港一啲獨特性，包括咗土地契約。誒喺而家嘅安排底下咧，係獲得豁免。誒法例亦都安排咗另一啲嘅豁免，包括匯票啦、提單啦、信用狀、公司章程，針對僱員嘅僱傭合約條款等等。而第三者咧必須符合兩項檢驗嘅其中一項咧。
先至能夠係誒強制執行。
畀佢嘅權益噉，第一就係合約本身已經規定咗第三者可以強制執行。第二就係合約有賦予第三者相關權益嘅條件。若然合約本身冇容許第三者執行嘅意圖咧，第三者咧就不能透過相關嘅法例咧要求強制執行。呢兩項檢驗咧都係保障合約雙方。
令到咧法例嘅改革唔會令到合約方咧係引致無法估計嘅訴訟風險，亦都唔讓香港走向一個咧動接訴訟嘅社會。不過有利都有弊，呢個安排咧對於一啲度身訂造合約各方實力均等下簽訂嘅合約咧，都係一個合理嘅安排。不過訴訟門檻。
相對高咧，對簽約時議價能力低嘅一方咧係不利嘅。議價能力弱啲嘅方咧，我哋通常諗到就係消費者啦。頭先阿梁議員都有提過啦，大家都好清楚知道，其實好多嘅合約咧係由服務供應商啊已經係寫好，消費者簽約過程裏邊咧其實係冇太大。
大嘅修改空間嘅呢個問題咧，消委會其實都留意到嘅，所以喺佢嘅意見書亦都指出咗，即使引入條例草案咧，對於改善消費者作為合約第三方嘅權益咧，亦都冇實質太大嘅幫助。消委會因此建議咧，將上述兩項檢驗略為放寬，容讓消費者。
較容易作為第三者提出訴訟，以補充現時冇綜合保障消費者嘅條例。當然啦，法改會指保障消費者權益唔應該透過呢個條例落實，而條例草案根本嘅原則咧就係要尊重合約方嘅自由。若然按消委會嘅意見放寬咧，就違反咗立約自由嘅原則。
係。
主席，我認為啊呢個講法咧就啊納約自由呢個原則，如果放棄一啲度身訂造嘅合約，雙方議價能力相約嘅情況底下咧，都係非常合理嘅。但係正如我頭先講啦，睇翻好多誒合約嘅訂立咧，其實誒無論係喺資訊啦、技術啦，以至
至係知識方面咧，嗯。
合約方咧都未必處於一個均等嘅狀況，噉我哋隨便舉啲例子都會揾到嘅，例如消費者同銀行啊或者保險公司簽嘅合約，啊事實上雙方喺資訊技術同埋知識上咧係唔係完全嘅對等嘅。喺呢個考慮底下咧，如果降低消費者作為第三者強制執行嘅門檻，
咧，亦都係一種平衡。主席，我雖然明白咧呢個階段咧，當局係唔會考慮嘅。作為引入合約第三者權利條例草案嘅起步，我係支持，亦都明白呢個做法咧會更加讓社會各方接受。但係咧，我請當局咧就唔好啊，唔理解現實啊簽約嘅過程裏邊咧，確實有不少合約嘅。
定立合約方或者各方嗰個啊，無論喺資訊啦、技術同埋知識上咧，係有不均等嘅情況嘅。噉我誒民建聯咧係要求當局咧繼續監察本條例草案落實嘅情況喺下一輪檢討時候提出相關嘅修訂。本人僅此陳辭支持條例草案。
有冇其他嘢想發言？
如果冇，我現在就請律政司司長發言答辯。喺司長答辯之後，辯論即告結束。律政司司長。
主席，我喺今年三月向立法會提交《合約第三者權利條例草案》，由梁繼昌議員擔任主席嘅法案委員會已經係詳細審閲該條條例草案。我僅此衷心感謝梁繼昌議員、各法案委員會委員同埋有關團體。
嘅寶貴意見。
正如我響提交條例草案嘅時候指出，條例草案嘅目的係落實香港法律改革委員會響二零零五年九月發表嘅納約各方嘅相互關係報告書中有關改革普通法下合約各方相互關係原則嘅建議。
根據普通法嘅相互關係原則，非合約一方嘅人士簡稱第三者，唔能夠根據合約而取得或者係強制執行合約下邊嘅權利。呢一個原則往往令到合約各方唔能夠實現，令到第三者受惠嘅意願，引致。
致對受引致對第三者權利造成唔公平或者唔方便嘅情況，因此一直係受到批評。
條例草案容許合約各方按其意願賦予第三者可強制執行嘅合約權利。簡而言之，假如合約各方嘅用意係容許第三者可強制執行合約，則條例草案可以落實合約。
各方嘅意願，為第三者提供更直接嘅法律途徑，強制執行合約。
若果合約各方係唔希望條例草案嘅條文適用於合約，亦都可以喺合約裏邊定明。
條例草案唔單止能夠進一步完善香港嘅合約法制度，亦都可以令香港嘅合約法同其他嘅主要普通法司法管轄區，包括英國、澳洲同埋新西蘭等嘅有關法律看齊。
稍後我會動議兩項嘅委員會審議階段修正案，呢啲嘅修正案全部係獲法案委員會同意。我現作簡單嘅介紹條例草案第三括弧二條定明新嘅法律規定係唔會適用於某啲類。
類別嘅合約，其中一類嘅合約係關乎土地嘅契約，包括公契。但係由於公契可能再有並非關乎土地嘅條款，因此我哋建議修訂條例草案第三括弧二條，以明確將公約中所
所有嘅條款以及關乎土地嘅契約列入條例草案不適用嘅合約類別範圍。
此外，我哋係建議對條例草案英文第八括弧二嘅條稍微修訂，務求可以完善呢一條嘅表達方式。
主席，正如我剛才指出，若果條例草案獲得通過，將會有助完善香港嘅合約法；而修訂建議則可以進一步完善條例草案嘅內容。我僅此陳詞，懇請議員支持二讀合約第三者。
權力條例草案以及我哋稍後動議嘅各項修正案，多謝主席。
我現在向各位提出嘅代決議題係《合約第三者權利條例草案》予以議讀，現在鼓勵表決，贊成嘅請舉手。
反對嘅請舉手。
我認為議題獲得在席議員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲得通過。合約第三者權利條例草案。
全體委員會審議階段，本會現在成委。